hello this is actin flop guest stream
number 21.1
it's april 21st 2022 and we're here with
shannon prox and shannon will be giving
a talk coordination dynamics of
multi-agent interaction
the talk
will happen for maybe around an hour and
then there'll be time for q a so feel
free to ask any questions in the chat
during so off to you shannon looking
forward to this talk and thanks again
for joining on acting flag
awesome thanks so much
um so i'm shannon daniel's already given
you
the title of our talk
and i'm coming to you from the
university of california in merced um
where i'm a phd candidate
and i'll actually be defending this
summer so maybe the next time you hear
from me
i'll be talking to you from
augustana university where i will be
starting a tenure track professor
position
later this fall as an assistant
professor of psychology and neuroscience
um
oh applause nice thanks
so that said i'm not going to talk to
you about neuroscience today i'm going
to talk to you a little bit about the
behavior of crowds
and i stole this roadmap idea from
previous active inference lab sessions
and this is kind of outlining
where we'll be going today
so first the first thing we're going to
do
is really dig into a little bit of
theory and data
i'm going to give a bit of a brief
introduction to multi-agent interaction
and what kind of human behavior i'm
interested in
and i'm going to walk through a couple
of ways that
active inference folks might be
interested in crowd dynamics and
behavior
but primarily i'm going to be focusing
on dynamical systems theory and the
notion of synergies and the tools that
come along with these concepts
and then finally i'm going to show you
a model system where we apply these
tools to a system of coupled metronomes
before i look at some empirical data
from real real-world interaction
of musical performance and also of uh
crowds
cheering at a basketball game
so first what is multi-age interaction
um this is simply an interaction that's
happening between two or more agents in
our case we're looking at people
and each of these people they'll have
their own personal goals and behaviors
but their individual behaviors are
influenced in some way by interacting
with other agents in their shared
environment
and i want to talk about two forms of
multi-agent coordination today
and the best way to introduce this is
through a short thought experiment
so
i'll just have you imagine the sounds of
a crowded coffee shop
consider how individuals in that coffee
shop might be interacting with each
other
there might be some small groups there
might be pairs
but mostly it's many individuals
engaging in small temporary interactions
and these individuals aren't
coordinating with every other individual
in some sort of cohesive coffee shop
group they're just a jumble of
individual individuals who are
cohabiting a shared space
now instead
imagine the audience on the floor of a
rock concert they're cheering or singing
along with the artists on the stage
and alternatively imagine the fan
section at your favorite sporting event
emerging into a synchronous chant or a
course of resounding booze
imagine how individuals in these large
crowds might be interacting with each
other
as they cheer sing chant or boo
they're all sharing in similar
behavioral states engaging in similar
actions they're likely sharing similar
physiological states like breathing
rates and neural states as well
these crowds are changing together in
time they're behaving and they're
coordinating like one large
interdependent group
and you could refer to these as shared
acoustic spaces
and they include various levels of
interaction from dyads pairs of
individuals or larger and larger groups
and i might even call these acoustic
social worlds
the acoustic signal that's generated by
these crowds it carries some information
about their behavioral dynamics that
were employed in creating that signal
and the sounds these crowd makes carry
some sort of information about the
status of that crowd either as an
internet incidental collection of lots
of individual coffee goers or an
integrated and coordinated crowd like a
crowd of concert goers
and there are of course many
important factors at play when we're
evaluating these acoustic social worlds
and we're trying to decide whether that
crowd is acting as one integrated
multi-agent system rather than a
collection of independent agents
and these include the social context a
coffee shop is different than a concert
arena
the development of pattern cultural
practices in these different contexts
and different scripts surrounding what
events happen and when these events
happen
and different regimes of shared
attention between each of these agents
and these are things you've talked about
in the inference lab before
um and basically this is all a rather
long-winded way of saying that we expect
coffee shop behavior in a coffee shop
and concert behavior in a concert arena
if i were going to talk to you
in the language of active inference i
might talk to you today about markov
blankets
and we might talk about this statistical
boundary um that might be behind a pair
of interacting individuals around a pair
of interacting individuals separating
their internal states of this
interaction with the rest of the
interactions happening in a coffee stop
crowd
and i might talk about how the
statistical boundary expands as we start
to engage or interact with larger groups
of people from three to four to maybe
100 people or more if we're in a large
group interaction
and while this can be a really useful
way
to model multi-agent interaction to talk
about a suite of nested markov blankets
we quickly run into questions
of how a researcher chooses where to
draw a markup blanket at any given
system
or where to draw each nested markup
blanket in a given system and this is a
topic that you've discussed a lot in the
active inference lab
you've spent some time
talking with yellow brunette berg and
colleagues
after their recent bbs article
commentaries and how there might be
differences from me as a researcher
applying some sort of markov blanket
around a system versus the actual
agents interacting in that system
but i just mentioned this idea of markov
blankets to situate the topic for the
audience of these interactive inference
lab live streams
as far as measuring uh the emergence of
an integrated interacting crowd
this is an empirical question that i'm
asking rather than a modeling question
and i'm not a mathematician or a modeler
so for this question about groups of
interacting people i found empirical
tools from dynamical systems theory and
with the concept of interpersonal
synergies
so that's what i'm going to introduce to
you guys next
so dynamical systems theory
this considers a trajectory of behavior
of a system over time
and the concept of synergies arises from
the field of motor control as a solution
to the degrees of freedom problem so
essentially the degrees of freedom
problem is that
fine and precise control of every degree
of freedom in a motor movement would be
computationally intractable for the
nervous system to solve
and what you see here is
a minor hammering
and you see these light patterns this is
really sort of the earliest sort of
motion capture that we had
and we're seeing the trajectory of his
arm
hammering here and you can see that even
though the hammer is hitting the same
place every time you'll have to trust me
that's hitting the same place every time
his arm is taking a slightly different
trajectory to get there but it generally
covers this one swinging behavior
and that's because the muscles in his
arm here are self-organizing
into coupled and locally constrained
degrees of freedom forming temporary
soft assemblies of motor function that's
enabling this flexible movement and
coordination here
put another way
synergies are identified by their
functional specific specificity
dimensional compression and reciprocal
compensation
what are those
well the need to perform a specific
function like hammering that anvil
that functional specificity
temporarily shapes the coordination of
several components into one system
that's dimensional compression
in which external and internal
perturbations are flexibly dealt with
via compensatory adjustments of
the components reciprocal compensation
so each muscle in his arm is
compensating for the activity of the
other muscle
and if he was bumped slightly there
would be compensation from other muscles
to ensure that anvil hits its location
and this is all done in order
to preserve the functionality of the
whole system for as long as it's needed
and that last comment for as long as
it's needed that gets to the notion of
soft assembly
um where
any of these units in this picture here
might be functionally
coupled just for as long as you need to
perform that task so if we're talking
about a group of people
these this group of people might form
some sort of complex system just while
they're interacting for that meeting
while they're at that concert until they
disperse
and are ready to move on
um
we can differentiate mere coordination
on which might happen between two people
as a result of engaging with the same
stimulus and similar patterns of actions
from a true interpersonal synergy
and you see here we might see the same
patterns of movement if we have two
individuals who are maybe just listening
to the same set of music
but if these
individuals are interacting with each
other where the action of one person and
the action of the second person
is constraining each other then this is
where an interpersonal synergy happens
these synergies are the result of these
micro scale structures of a system
giving rise to macro scale dynamics
when a synergy develops we no longer
need to describe the independent
dynamics of each micro scale structure
we can instead describe the behavior of
this single interaction dominance system
which consists of complementary actions
from each person's motor activity as it
pertains to their role in this softly
assembled complex system
and you might even notice some
similarities here between
these graphics and a graphic we might
draw of nested markov blankets and these
might very well be two sides of the same
coin um just two perspectives with a
very similar conceptual landscape here
and there's a variety of methods for
studying the coordination dynamics that
underlie interpersonal coordination
for example we might ask two people to
sit next to each other and swing
pendulums or to rock and rocking chairs
and we can measure how these individuals
intentionally or unintentionally
synchronize their behavior
as each individual's action becomes
coupled to their partner
or we can ask musicians to play together
in a musical ensemble or a duet
and we can measure how these quartets or
duets move together in time forming
these loosely coupled interpersonal
synergies
but in each of these interactions
a motor or acoustic behavioral output of
each interacting individual was measured
and analyzed for meaningful correlations
between these individuals
so importantly in these experiments here
it has been possible to obtain clear
measurements of individual behavior
in order to correlate the behavior of
these individuals and examine the
emergent coordination dynamics of
multi-agent interaction and social
self-organization
but what happens when we have this
massive crowd of people
can we measure the interpersonal
synergies that form in such a large
crowd
how does a group of people move between
novel and habitual
patterns of coordination how does a
multi-agent system navigate transitions
between chaos and stability
and let's make it a little bit trickier
the real world is messy and measurement
is difficult in a naturalistic social
interaction and a very large crowd i
probably can't measure the behavior of
every single individual person
i probably can't give everyone an
individual microphone i probably can't
track each person's individual brain
states and i might not even have access
to a camera let alone a set of motion
capture cameras and hundreds of markers
to track everyone's head and limb
movements
so let's come back to the crowds we
imagined at the start of this discussion
when you're imagining this coffee shop
crowd and the crowd at the rock concert
you might have also been imagining how
these concert how these crowds sounded
so the difference between
this disjointed noise you might hear at
the coffee shop and this
all together coordinated singing maybe
at a rock concert it's trivial trivially
easy for you or i to identify
an uncoordinated group of independent
individuals
happening to co-exist in a shared space
versus a coordinated group of
interdependent
group members in a crowd
we can simply hear that these two groups
of people sound different
similarly we can simply hear when we
ourselves are engaged in participating
as a collective sort of agent while
we're interacting with a large group of
people
or in a very large musical ensemble
so i'm taking that idea
and
i think we can measure the sounds that a
crowd makes and with a well-placed
microphone or a few microphones
we can generate a single audio recording
of the sounds that an interacting group
makes over time
and i know that a human can make
inferences about the interactions and
the acoustic social world of a crowd
just by listening
um so similarly
i want to know if this dynamical systems
toolkit that i have can allow us to make
inferences about the behavior of an
entire complex system
based on this one acoustic measurement
that we have access to
so for the next little while i'm going
to walk through a bit of theory and then
a toy example
until i eventually end this talk with
data from real live multi-agent groups
that we're analyzing with tools from
dynamical systems theory
so
one of our most simple
complex dynamical systems
is a
metronome or a pendulum
so christopher huygens first discovered
this activity of two pendulums from from
pendulum clocks
will be related to each other when these
clocks are hanging from a shared surface
and what he found was that these
pendulums would swing in anti-synchrony
with each other
and since then in
1600s or so there's been lots of
research on pendulums and on coupled
metronomes
and if we put these metronomes a time
keeping device um
for for making music on a shared
platform and maybe that platform rotates
like this
um you'll see each of these metronomes
come into synchrony with each other
these are just static pictures so to
really help you visualize this and hear
this i'm recruiting a little bit of help
from the mythbusters
the mythbusters on youtube
so hopefully it is uh free and
uncopyrighted
and i'm just going to skip ahead here to
part way into their episode
friction and momentum as i can so that
only the metronome is having the effect
now let's try to
adam doubles his trouble with two
metronomes set to the same tick mark
look at the movement on this platform
and after two minutes the shimmy takes
over
stay with it boys
nice
nice it's totally working
it just took them a little while to find
each other's rhythm
cool
i have an idea if i stop the platform
they should drop out of phase
there it is
the moving platform is totally totally
critical to this experiment
so
all right so that's uh adam savage there
with two
metronomes one on earth why does this
matter um well what he's done is
replicated that findings of that
centuries-old experiment that was
originally conducted with pendulums on a
clock
and
he noted that this moving platform here
is what's totally totally critical
but what i want you to also think of is
that you heard these metronomes slowly
coming into phase with each other they
were becoming interdependent on each
other's behavior because they are
connected by this coupling mechanism
here this the shared platform
and as adam correctly notes this moving
platform is totally totally critical and
in fact when you saw him stop the
platform the metronomes were no longer
coupled and their behavior no longer
affects the other
this platform here can take many forms
as long as it is freely flowing and
responsive to the metronomes movement
and for the metronomes this platform is
the essential coupling mechanism for
this emergent of coordinated acoustic
behavior
in humans this coordination doesn't have
to be a physical platform
in fact
i argue that it is the interaction
itself which serves as a coupling
mechanism for multi-agent human behavior
and we're going to spend just a little
bit more time with metronomes before i
get onto real human groups here
so when you have many metronomes on a
shared platform you can have more than
two
they're going to transition from
uncoordinated random phase to
coordinated synchronous phase and what
you're going to hear next is the
acoustic output of 32 metronomes on a
freely moving platform
and i'm going to justify to you two
things
that we can identify emergent
coordinated behaviors in acoustic data
and what all
i'm going to justify what state-space
reconstruction is and how this tool from
dynamical systems can help us to analyze
that acoustic data
so i'm going to start at the beginning
with each of the metronomes in random
phase
and this really takes a bit of a time so
we don't have to listen to that for so
long i'm going to skip ahead
[Laughter]
[Music]
so what you heard was 32 metronomes all
ticking at their own tempo at their
natural period it sounded like a bunch
of random noise
but this platform again served as a
coupling mechanism
and synchronization between the
metronomes emerge so they begin to sound
like one group ticking together and this
is an example of the type of data we'll
be investigating for the emergence of
coordination and acoustic signals
so keep these metronomes in mind
no don't don't play the metronomes again
the platform is serving as a coupling
mechanism a synchronization emerges they
begin to sound like one group
um so we're going to visit some theory
i'm going to introduce you to token's
theorem and phase based reconstruction
so if we take one time series from a
system this is the lorenz system here
it's defined by a set of three
differential equations um but what you
need to know is that we can reconstruct
the behavior of this system as a whole
by measuring only one of its parts
this is accomplished by embedding
delayed copies of a single time series
into multiple dimensions on some delay
so
here's
one of this time series extracted from
the learn system and we delay that time
series to make another time series delay
once more to make a third time series we
take these three dimensions and we use
them to reconstruct a projection of the
lorenz system and this is phase space
reconstruction
and you can see that it maintains the
topography or the same shape as the
original lorenz system
in the case of our acoustic data
i'm going to take a time series of that
sound that acoustic signal
and i'm going to follow these steps here
to
i'm going to follow these steps here to
reconstruct the behavior of those
metronomes over time
and once we've completed this
phase-based reconstruction i'm going to
visualize the behavior of our
reconstructed system by generating what
we call recurrent spots
this is done by plotting recurrent
points from the reconstructive phase
base within some radius that we set
and we can evaluate the structures in
these recurrence plots using recurrence
quantification analysis so on the right
here you're seeing a few examples of
different time series
and you're seeing their reconstructed
phase space here
and on the bottom you're seeing the
recurrence plot that we
generate from these reconstructed phase
space
so one of the simplest measures that we
can glean from our currents plot is the
rate that states recur and this is
called
recurrence rate
and on the left here we're seeing a time
series of a simple sine wave and when we
reconstruct it we end up seeing
something a bit like an oval or a circle
and when we plot a point on our
recurrent system every time a recurrent
spot here every time our system revisits
a space on the circle here
so in the sine waves recurrence plot
we're seeing these diagonal lines these
diagonal lines are reflecting
deterministic behavior
and they track how similar
similar sequences of values change over
time
so this sine wave here it's reliably
deterministic if it starts here it's
going to go here next then it's going to
go there next
and that gives us these long recurrence
values here
and as
you've probably expect this measure is
called determinism
in the middle we see uncorrelated white
noise and you can see the signal already
looks much more random than our sine
wave
and when we reconstruct it in face space
i don't really see a shape here that we
can
get much out of
and underneath you see our recurrence
plot and it looks similarly random you
could think of it like white noise on
your television even
finally on the right we see a time
series extracted from speech it's a
little bit deterministic like our sine
wave if it goes up it's going to come
down
but it's also drifting a bit and you can
see if we reconstruct that phase space
instead of a simple oval we're seeing
we're seeing a sort of transient signal
here
and in the recurrence plot
um we're also going to be seeing
variation in length in these diagonals
and finally recurrent spots can contain
these vertical structures that you don't
see here in addition to diagonals
and these are indications of periods of
stability we measure these with a value
called laminarity in laminarity you can
contrast it with determinism it measures
how a signal is organized in terms of
simple similar absolute values that are
stable over time
and this is
one representation of recurrence plots
it takes a little bit of time to get
comfortable with what our current spot
is so i just have a different
visualization to show you a little bit
of the same thing
so
these are the same set of rqa measures
that we take from our system and plot on
recurrent spots
this is demonstrating
recurrence rate it's just the percentage
of recurrent points that we see on this
recurrence plot over time and it
represents patterns of behavior that
repeat over time
determinism
is the percentage of points that
fall in a diagonal at any time and it
represents behaviors that belongs to a
longer sequence of behavior
entropy this is the variability and
lengths of these diagonal lines down
here
and it represents the amount of disorder
that there might be in these sequences
finally laminarity here are the
percentage of points that fall on a
vertical line and this represents
clusters of behavior that might repeat
for a length of time like when a system
revisits a period of behavior
leaves and returns that behavioral state
again
all right so it's a lot of theory i need
to bring you back to the metronome so we
know what's going on here
so what you see here this is a picture
of our uncoordinated metronomes they're
moving in all sorts of directions and
finally our coordinated metronomes at
the bottom
and i took 30 second a 30 second
acoustic signal from each
each set of behaviors here
and on the right i have signals from
this uncoordinated metronome and the
recurrent spot we generated from them
and you can see this first recurrent
spot it resembles that kind of
uncorrelated white noise i don't see a
lot of structure here
and then in our time series for the
coordinated metronomes you start to see
some periodicities kind of in this
signal here and you see a lot more of
these laminar structures down here in
the bottom these vertical structures
which indicate these periods of stable
states in this group metronome behavior
i could break that down even smaller and
i could look at five seconds of sound
and we see the same structures emerging
you can also see a bit more clearly
these spikes that occur in the
coordinated metronomes that correlate
with these vertical structures than we
did in the last plot
so this is great now you're experts
you've learned everything you need to
know to evaluate the emergence of
coordination
when we measure it from a global
acoustic signal and you know how to
visualize it in a recurrence plot and
how to interpret that plot so we're
going to apply all of this to human data
and i want to remember for the
metronomes this platform is the
essential coupling mechanism for the
emergence of coordinated behavior
for humans
the interaction is totally totally
critical
so say me and my colleague marley reeves
from the applied mathematics department
here uc merced
so we don't need a shared platform
instead we just need to interact with
other human beings in order to couple
our multi-agent human behavior
so now that we've got this far
i promised you some empirical data
and i'm going to tell you about
multi-agent interaction first in a
specific musical ensemble performing a
specific musical work
and then in the crowd at a basketball
game
so first our musical ensemble here
um
they are performing a work called
welcome to the imagination world by
tsuki shimizu
and this group of musicians um they're
performing this piece that was composed
to do something interesting so the
composer wrote the first few minutes of
this musical piece to be completely
random in music theory terms we call
this aliatwork it's when some element of
the music is left up to chance or to
whatever the performers decide to play
in that moment
so the start of this piece sounds a
little bit like this
[Music]
[Applause]
so
[Music]
[Applause]
okay that flute gets a little loud for
me um so this is not the musicians
warming up on stage this is the actual
music
the musicians themselves are instructed
not to interact with each other
and you can see this is kind of hard for
musicians
because you do hear
musicians sort of taking turns starting
each musical line a little bit
and it's a little bit hard to play
completely random you hear some folks
playing scales up and down but in
general this is supposed to sound
random and they're not supposed to be
coordinated
and after a few minutes the musical
score actually directs the musicians to
begin coordinating with each other and
when this happens i'll show you what
that sounds like
[Music]
so
[Applause]
[Music]
i'm gonna stop it right before it gets
exciting
um so once they've been coordinating
with each other they begin to sound like
one interacting musical ensemble
so this musical interaction is serving
as the coupling mechanism
and the coordination between the
musicians arises and they begin to sound
like one interacting ensemble
now we're not seeing emergent or
spontaneous interaction in this
particular musical composition and this
performance the musicians are told by
the musical score precisely when to
begin coordinating their actions
and
in this particular performance the
divide between uncoordinated and joint
music making is made even more apparent
by a theatrical trick the lights turn on
and then the conductor arrives on stage
just as the musicians begin to play
together as one ensemble but i'm using
this as a model system because i know
the behavior they're supposed to be
engaged and i know that there's going to
be a transition from uncoordinated to
coordinated behavior
so i can use that knowledge to ask the
questions
are there any differences in non-linear
recurrence dynamics measured by rqa
between the uncoordinated acoustic
behavior and the coordinated behavior of
this musical ensemble
and
spoiler alert there absolutely are so at
the top you're seeing um the first and
last 30 seconds of that first piece the
first part of the performance
on the bottom you're seeing the first
and last 30 seconds of the second part
of the performance once the musicians
have become coordinated
and we can see that the acoustic
behavior from these musicians and the
coordinated section of the music is more
structured we see these bursty vertical
lines here
um with where you have these stretches
of connected sound connected stretches
of sound um for
periods of time
and again we can look even closer
at five second samples and we can see
the same structures
in
same vertical structures in the
coordinated but not the uncoordinated
sections so if i take just
these little blocks here
zoom in to five seconds we see a little
bit more structure here and a little bit
less or a little bit noisier structure
here
um these are just for visualizations
this is not actually the five second
snippet here
but it works for
getting the idea across
okay so cool i see these structures in
the recurrence plot
but is it really more structured
when musicians are coordinated
we can do some statistics and we can
visualize our data
in another way so these are
distributions of all of those measures
that we extract extracted from the
recurrent spot
and you can see
coordinated sections in blue
uncoordinated sections in red and we're
seeing that when the musicians begin
interacting with each other as a
coordinated musical ensemble
recurrence and stability measures
increased overall so we have higher also
more variable rqa measures
when they're coordinated and we see
lower and less variable rqa measures
when they're uncoordinated
and we can see this even a little more
clearly
if we can
plot
those same measures over time
and
the blue and purple lines here are
representing uncoordinated section of
the piece orange and green is
represented sorry blue and purple is
coordinated
orange and green is uncoordinated
and we can see that over time when the
musicians are coordinated and acting
like one
interacting ensemble they're able to
explore a greater variety of recurrence
dynamics they're able to explore
more behavioral states than when they're
uncoordinated and we see all of these
measures no matter what they are
hovering around a small subset of
dynamics
now you would be forgiven if you are
skeptical of these results after all the
entire musical performance is over eight
minutes long maybe i simply chose the
most uncoordinated sections and the most
uncoordinated sections of the song
and you'd be smart to have this worry
our peer reviewers shared the same worry
so
we graphed the time series of rqa
metrics for the entire piece and it's
pretty clear even if you don't know what
these values are that there's some
difference in all of these top pink and
blue kind of graphs and these bottom
orange and green type of graph
we're seeing this same greater
variability
greater values and more variability in
each of these rqa metrics
when the musicians are coordinated than
when they are performing as a bunch of
individuals on stage
and the takeaway here
is that
these musicians when they're interacting
together as a musical ensemble they're
able to explore a greater variety of
acoustic behavior when they're when they
formed a single
complex system an interpersonal synergy
then when they were acting as a lot of
individuals on stage and we were able to
use these non-linear statistical methods
from dynamical systems theory to measure
that change
cool so that's a musical ensemble
i'm using it as a model system because
we know what the behavior should be
can i measure this
from a different kind of system one that
doesn't have a script dictating the
behavior of what's going on on the stage
so to do that i look at data recorded
from
the student section of a byu basketball
game
and this data
was collected by butler and colleagues
and labeled by
many hard-working undergraduate students
and we have basically recordings
from the crowd that are labeled based on
what kind of
crowd sounds they're making whether
they're cheering this is like a loud
positive crowd vocally vocalization
um whether they're applauding so this is
mostly clapping but could include some
vocalization
um distraction noise when you're trying
to distract someone from a free throw
mainly
um positive chance so this is the
fans chanting um their
their byu cougars chants or defense
um negative chanting it's when they're
angry rather than cheering positively
singing and then silence
so
we're taking this data and we're going
to ask a similar question so we don't
have a clear transition from
uncoordinated to coordinated behavior
but we do have all of these different
types of behavior
so
we're going to ask is there a
relationship between non-linear
recurrence dynamics measured by rqa and
these different categories of acoustic
behavior
at the crowd at this basketball game
we follow the same process
we extract acoustic signals
and we cut them up into five second
samples here
and we use these signals to generate
recurrence plots
and we take the measures from that
recurrence plot to see if there's
anything different and i'm going to show
you just to recurrent spot in the next
slide i'm going to show you a plot from
positive chanting and from distraction
noise
so here's distraction noise
it looks like white noise it looks
like what you would see
on your television screen
and when i show you positive chance
there's clearly a striking difference
there's almost no structure in this
distraction noise here but there are
very clear laminar bursts of activity
represented in these vertical lines
and in fact these two plots look very
similar to our unsynchronized and
synchronized metronomes way back from
the middle of this talk
and intuitively this makes sense if
you're trying to distract someone during
a free throw you're making all sorts of
random sounds you might be shaking your
keys around people are stomping on the
stands but if you're cheering your team
on trying to motivate them to score more
points or if you're mounting a strong
defense you're going to be working
together shouting whatever your chant is
go team go defense and it's going to
occur in a very rhythmic metronomic
faction
and we can compare how all of these
distributions of rqa metrics look
between each different kind of crowd
noise
and you can see there's quite a lot of
overlap but there's also some difference
so positive and negative chance seem to
be a bit similar to each other in every
category which makes sense because
whether they're chanting in a positive
or negative energy it's still this
rhythmic isochronous behavior that's
happening
um distraction noise cheer and applause
on the other hand all seem pretty
similar to each other no matter where we
look at them
and then finally all the way on the
lowest scale is angry noise here
um and one
thing to note is we had very
very few samples of angry noise here so
that could be why we're seeing a few of
these differences and if we had more
samples maybe ingrid noise would look a
bit more like distraction noise
so visually we can see there are
differences in these rqa metrics for all
of these crowd sounds
and we don't want to just do
visuals so we can do some statistics
here
this is just another visualization
of our estimated marginal means showing
pairwise comparisons between every crowd
sound category and it's a graphical
representation of the estimated marginal
means if these red lines overlap that
means there are not significant
differences
between um for instance distract noise
cheering applause here
positive and negative do look different
however
interesting um and then angry noise is
far out by itself
um so knowing this um i mentioned very
briefly earlier i have a colleague in
the applied mathematics department and
one thing she's interested in is whether
we can give a machine learning algorithm
some of these rqa metrics to tell the
difference between these different crowd
sounds
the researchers at byu have done this
with traditional sound metrics spectral
analysis captural analysis and we're
doing it with our rqa metrics so we're
focused more on the rhythmic content
rather than pitch or spectral content of
the sound
and she
is doing this in two ways so one is
training a
neural network with
image classification
and
what i'm going to show you a few results
from is a random forest that is using
these recurrent features as input and
doing some future vector classification
using decision trees
and doing some stuff that if you ask me
questions about i will not know the
answer
because i'm not the mathematician in
this context but
once she's trained that algorithm
it can actually learn the differences
between these crowd sounds so if these
are dark blue along the diagonal that
means that it categorized cheer very
well if they're light blue that means
there was some confusion here
um
and if we remember
through one of the previous graphs
applause distraction noise all kind of
look similar to each other so if we sort
of smush those
into one distraction category um put
applause and share together and put
positive negative chance here um we get
even better classification and this part
is something we're still working on
hopefully we will be ready to submit in
a paper kind of soon
um but now that we're ending on this
really complex point
um what have we learned
first we took a
quick dive into dynamical systems theory
and the notion of interpersonal
synergies i told you that interpersonal
synergies form when a functional
coupling emerges between the behavior of
two or more individuals this kind of
synergy can arise when individuals begin
to coordinate and as an integrated
multi-aging group of people
but measuring the submergence of
coordination in large groups of people
is difficult even if we can intuitively
hear the difference between a coffee
shop crowd and a crowd at a concert or
sporting event
without individual signals from each
person in this interacting group it's
very hard for scientists to measure when
the coordination occurs
but if we can hear this difference then
maybe we can measure it so we practice
with the toy model a pair of coupled
metronomes transitioning from
uncoordinated to coordinated activity
unsynchronized to synchronized and then
we applied these same non-linear
statistical analysis techniques from
dynamical systems to measure
uncoordinated and coordinated behavior
in a musical ensemble
transitioned once too far
ah my musical ensemble is behind our
graphs here apologies about that i can
come back to this slide
um so when we want to learn something
about social behavior music provides a
good model system you know
roughly and can manipulate what roles
each member of the musical group is
performing and sometimes you even have
the aid of a musical script like we did
to be able to carefully um
measure the coordination dynamics that
emerge in this joint music making
these same intentional interdependencies
which arise from a group of musicians
co-creating music together
can also emerge as the result of local
interaction between individuals and
large interaction groups of people like
crowds at a basketball game
and we investigated that by measuring
the different crowd sounds that these
fans made
and the different acoustic behavioral
dynamics we could observe in each of
these crowd sounds um with fans at a byu
basketball game
and
all this work i was not done just by me
um but also my colleague marley reeves
in the applied mathematics department
my advisor mesh bell super mania and
also our colleagues chris kello and
michael spivey
so that's all i got thank you so much
for having me
awesome thank you
you can unshare and
all ask some questions and if anyone in
the live chat has questions they can
also ask
sounds great are you going back to the
slides
i was going to go back to the slide i
also cannot find the unshare button
ah it's fine it's it's in jitsi the same
as the share button but yeah
cool
all right
well
a lot of very interesting research and
really appreciate the
care and to kind of
speaking it very concisely and clearly
so just if i could give one takeaway
that i thought was really fascinating
so you in the fuceroli 2014 quotation he
talked about how there was like synergy
and about the continuum
and the spaces that are
uncoordinated versus increasingly
coordinated from the sheet music which
is one type to the emergent coordination
and then
um
[Music]
i thought that was an interesting way to
open up coordination not in a framework
of either
strong versus weak emergence
but rather within a
directly measurable dynamical systems
perspective
and then at the end to
do the machine learning and be able to
train a model on the recurrence
statistics
and then identify the system it's like
there's information about the system
state as identified by experts which is
what that labeling task was about that's
retained like just in the coordination
pattern
and so there's something about the
patterns across systems that can be
generalized that captures also
important information
and that's an intuition that i think
people often bring
up when talking about dynamical systems
but i really thought it was made clear
with how you presented it
yeah thanks i'm glad that i got across
that was kind of a message i was trying
to share
one place to maybe start is this soft
assembly so where does this soft
assembly come into play and i guess just
what
does it mean in
human teams or communication
yeah um so this this notion of soft
assembly um
let me think of something that's not
soft something that's
hardwired if
oh i don't have i don't have an opposite
example to soft assembly so if you take
if you take like a
a tool
like i don't know a wrench it only can
move in one way the parts of the wrench
or the parts of a set of pliers they're
not softly assembled they're always
attached
and they're always going to perform that
function
right
but if we think about
lots of kind of systems if we think
about
human systems um
if we think about
um ant colonies or if we think about
anything where an individual member of
that system could leave if it wanted to
or could leave when they're not
interacting that's what we would call a
softly assembled system
and a group of humans
um
the example that i was thinking of was
any group of humans that comes together
um for some amount of time if we're
talking about musicians on stage
they're together and they function as a
string quartet or as an orchestra so
long as they're on stage and performing
together but then they can pack their
instruments up and they can go home so
there's not a strong bond or like a
strong
physical
mechanical connection that's forcing
their interaction
to occur
it's just happening during that process
because you also connected that to like
the transient motor
chains and so that was
pretty
um
interesting
again anyone who's watching live can ask
a question otherwise i'll just keep on
asking about a few points so
you use the metronome as a
example of synchronization
but also there's listening to repetitive
music
whether it's like electronic music
that's repetitive or other kinds of
music
uh
binaural beats so
what
is this repetition listening
nature and what like kind of makes us
select a given level of repetition to
desire
like what how do we think about that in
terms of how you presented it with the
recurrence here
yeah so there's two things that i would
i would think about so first you
mentioned um binaural beats and we
want to listen to these very repetitive
musical patterns
um and so
there's two ways that
our brains might be interpreting
rhythmic patterns
in music um one notion that is probably
very meaningful to the active inference
lab and what you talk about
um is is predictive coding
um and the idea that we have
um these hierarchical predictions that
are happening in the brain so when we
perceive this low-level stimulus this
rhythmic input
we're constantly predicting when the
next input is going to arrive
and we're only passing up areas when our
prediction is wrong
and
isochronous these very rhythmic beats
are really easy to predict
um but there's another option it could
be that we're not doing any prediction
at all and we just have these inherent
oscillations these natural frequencies
of oscillations in our brain
and
when we hear a rhythmic pattern
that is similar enough
we
naturally entrain to that beat or that
rhythm
drives this oscillatory behavior and so
you have
this emergent entrainment and no
predictions necessary
and you could be in either camp
i alternate between being a firmly
predictive coding camp and being a
entrainment camp
um but this
either way um what seems to be really
important in this activity is activity
of your motor system and your ability
for your motor system which is really
good at making periodic movements like
moving walking
um the ability of the motor system to
help
the auditory system to communicate with
the auditory system
um in
predicting when the next speed occurs or
in entraining to the beat of a sound
like that
um
and that's with binaural beats the
second thing that i would bring up
is
we like these binaural beasts maybe
they're relaxing for some people
um but we're listening to music there's
a phenomenon called musical groove
um and this
is when it's very scientific no it is
actually the scientific term um peter
gennada in 2012 uh coined this and it's
uh when the rhythm of the music is it's
just complicated enough
that it makes us want to move to music
so it's just in that sweet spot where
it's
predictable but not quite predictable
enough
and it engages our motor system instead
of just passively engaging it
it actually makes us move to the beat of
the music
this might be because when we move when
we tap our foot when we dance we're
better able to predict when the next
beat happens
thanks the the groove uh again jargon so
apologies
it it
reminds me of the zone of proximal
development
and kind of what does it mean if there
was a build up and too much tension
being built like a ramping but then
there's for example um when there's
quarter notes for two measures and then
eighths and then sixteens and then it's
like when it goes even faster and then
it
it's like a meme with making it more
exciting
because there it's reflecting a
uh
cultural and
potentially related to biology like our
priors on
increasing rate of
the the
sound is like meaning something because
it can't go on forever so then something
is exciting or something is changing so
then that's very interesting about how
our
like what is quiet what is loud what do
those represent and what are the priors
of the musical experience
that becoming cultured in different ways
so
yeah maybe how does it help us think
about like different preferences amongst
individuals
in the kind of music that they want to
play
or engage in or listen to or how they
want to
engage with that music
yeah so
so much so much content and what you
just said
um
the one is is this like notion of
anticipation when the rhythm keeps
getting faster and faster
um and
there's um
a whole book by leonard meyer about
how
music
is correlated with emotions and how
there's this idea that a composer is
playing with these periods of tension
and release so whether that tension is
from build-up of rhythmic events and we
usually expect
the faster rhythm gets maybe
it's associated with
a certain
activity in the music or we expect it to
slow down after it's gotten faster for
so long
or you're thinking about um when the
beat drops in a piece of electronic
music
for instance
um
we can play with the rhythm or we can
play with the musical pitch and we might
have a certain set of chords that
usually lead up to a certain resolution
and we can trick everyone in the
audience if we play a different chord
instead
um but you mentioned
this kind of idea of different
individuals
liking different kinds of music and this
zone of proximal development too so
this is really getting into how
the music that we're exposed to
shapes the expectations that we're going
to have
so if you grew up
hearing western music if you
are trained in western classical music
you have certain expectations of what
rhythms are allowed
of
what kind of melodic or harmonic
progression is going to happen
and when you hear a different kind of
music
it might not even register to you as
music the first time you hear it until
you learn about it until you learn about
the music of that culture
um
even if it's music within your own
culture say you listen to uh
hard rock for the first time or like
like heavy metal for the first time it
might just sound like noise
until you're exposed to it enough or if
you study the patterns of of how that
music
um moves in time
it's like the
plastic learning phase which is always
continuing but especially during early
developmental phases
uh
it it's
catching on to patterns and rhythms and
whether the the beat measure
or different pitches and
rhythms are familiar
or not that's very
interesting area so
i would one model that and or where do
you see active inference in this
discussion and what you've discussed
here
yeah so there's um been predictive
coding approaches at modeling this
um also the information dynamics of
music
is one model that comes to mind
um
or if you think of any of these ai music
generators um
google has an ai that plays music like
bach
um actually that might not be google but
there is an ai that plays music like
bach
google has
uh
different music ais that you can
actually interact with
and what you do here
is you turn all of the music into
symbols for the computer
um and you're going to encode
what the pitch is you're going to encode
what the the rhythm is and a set of
however many different numbers you want
and then
you can kind of take measures of maybe
the shannon entropy of how likely you
are to expect this note knowing that
that note has played
and if you've only trained this ai on
bach corrals maybe then you know the
notes are mostly going to be quarter
notes maybe half notes maybe an eighth
note here there and some whole notes so
you already are constrained with the
type uh the the length of note that
you're going to hear
and black corrals follow the a similar
pattern every single chorale
so you have
you know the probability of you hearing
the tonic chord at this point in time
and not hearing um a major second
or
hearing a
certain
step
at this point in time um because you've
mapped out all of those probabilities
and lots of people do that i don't
do that kind of um
ai or modeling work
with musical scores myself
so they're creating musical scores
with what
imperative or
for what ends
that's a good question so
um
i've actually worked with a co-author
with submitted manuscript
and that's kind of one of the questions
we ask
um
waiting on reviews back but
we're looking at all of these different
kind of music making ais
and
we're coming at the question from
another angle we're kind of asking
whether they can make
music and whether it's good music um
and what's missing if they can't
um
and that's because when we're talking
about humans and why humans make music a
lot of it comes down to the social
interaction that music allows
so music seems to facilitate social
bonding
if i
am drumming in time with you even if i'm
walking in time with you but if i'm
doing something in time with you
whether it's drumming or tapping or
making music
i probably will like you more after that
event
um
and
it's also a tool that we use um
parents to infants to soothe them if you
think about lullabies
and there's a lot about music that seems
to be rooted in social bonding
and music also activates
reward systems in our brain
so
we get a dopamine rush when we get to
that peak experience in music
um we
there's some recent work and i can't
remember who put it out that if you
listen to music um you're getting
similar
activation as if you had to engage in
exercise
we use music and therapy and like music
is just it's connected to a lot of
survival and social bonding functions
for humans
but why doesn't ai make music
like
the ai doesn't need to bond with another
ai um
maybe they're getting reward in terms of
like a value function that we've
programmed into the ai to say like oh
good that was a good musical line that
you made
now do it again
but like what motivation do they have
there's also no connection to any sort
of like interreceptive states or
physiological states if we think about
listening to music before we go to the
gym we listen to music to hype us up and
get us pumped and it's raising our blood
pressure
it's
getting us our body prepared to do the
activity we want to do and at night we
might listen to calming soothing music
lower blood pressure lower breathing
rate
to prepare to go to sleep
what drive does a computer have
to sort of maintain these different sort
of
homeostatic needs at different times of
the day or times of your life
compared to a human it's a great
question
i don't know if the people who are
making ai music
are always asking that question
um but have you ever heard of holly
herndon
no
so she is a um
electronic music creator who has created
a music ai in this space and her notion
was to take
this idea of of cultural learning um and
if you could think of the zone of
proximal development but she has she's
trained her her ai baby
um with voices of a lot of different
people and exposed to a lot of like
basically a culture in order for it to
generate some sort of music
um from what she makes and she has some
really interesting art in that space
it's a little bit like the the tree
falling in the forest is it a noise or a
sound someone have to listen to it if
you have
a bunch of auto-generated songs
in a genre but no human experience
writing them
know and experience listening to them
it's like did it ever happen
um that's quite an interesting idea and
it's also it's a cross-media issue with
generated text and image
and uh
that also
makes me think about a john cage quote
talking about music
and duration and time so maybe
what do you think about music and time
music and time
so
stereotypically whenever we think of
john cage think of that four minutes and
33 seconds
he sits in front of the piano and starts
a timer and it's just silent
um
there's a
marius kozak i i if i remember right um
actually writes about um music and time
and the idea that
um
music is deeply linked to movement
in time and it's sort of it's sort of a
way to
express movement in time
through
not just the auditory lens but also
through dance so like thinking of dance
it's a form of music as well and seeing
how
not not only something like auditory
music but dance is prevalent in every
culture
in the globe
and i think there's something important
to
the notion of time and maybe music as
the choreographing
of movement through time
because if we think about
you mentioned
generated language or images
these are
static pieces you know you can look
around the scene or you can read the the
text but music has to happen in the
temporal domain you have to listen to it
over a period of time once a note is
played
it's gone after that or once you've um
enacted a particular dance
it's gone after that
um
and i don't know i don't have like a a
nice
way to wrap that up about why time is
important
um
but it's definitely an important feature
of music and of dance that's you're not
going to find in
other art forms you might find you could
think of it in a narrative has to happen
over time because you're reading it over
time
and that's part of why so in my
neuroscience work i study how we
perceive musical rhythm
so
if we
perturb the time
that a musical rhythm is happening
how does our brain cope with that
or if we perturb
part of the brain that is thought to be
involved with
timing perception so this ability to
hear
beats that are happening in a certain
phase
or
to hear certain rhythms if we perturb
that system
are we going to impair how
people perceive the rhythm in that piece
of music
and these are questions i'm asking
questions a lot of people are asking
um
it's a very
bright landscape right now for that kind
of question
what's really
interesting about bringing the action in
and maybe even moving music
outside or a little bit beyond just the
auditory
because that might open up auditory
experiences that aren't music
and musical experiences that have a
large component um through time but
they're not necessarily auditory
now so one other
thing thinking about the the development
of auditory preferences and expectations
for
probably a long time in human history
the sounds and the music that one heard
was local and like performed if not
interactive
and then there was a pretty short period
of time of like
top 40 records cds and then now there's
the ability to listen to
a huge number of
music as well as listen to
a small selection many times
and uh
what is that doing
to our auditory cognition or or even
more broadly
that i can listen to the same
song with 50 different versions in a row
versus that just not being plausible
not even so long ago
yeah that's an interesting question i
haven't thought a lot about it but
um
i'm basically just tracking like from
music in the home to everybody's hearing
everything the same thing on the radio
to now we have spotify
and the internet um
and it's probably a question that's not
just about music it's also about media
we went from
only getting our media or news from
people that we locally interacted with
to everybody sitting for the same virus
i chat so now everybody's in their
different bubble for
whatever media they're consuming um
and it's interesting i know there's been
some work um for instance um mike hove
has looked at how
the bass sounds in music have gotten
lower over time lower and louder
um
which has some impact on how we feel
musical groove since the bass is usually
where the the rhythm sits um
in
pop music
um
but yeah so
what is it doing to like our brains and
like our perception of music
that's interesting you'd and you
mentioned
memes earlier
which made me think of tick tock
um
and so this like new way of
proliferating sounds
um and if you've ever been spent very
much time on tick-tock there'll be like
one sound that everybody's making a
dance to
or one sound that um people are just
playing over the top of the video of
their dogs running around because that
sounds popular
um and then when you hear it on the
radio
it's a little bit jarring because you
only know this like 15 second snippet or
however long a tick tock is
um from that tic tac video and then you
realize this is this is a real song like
a real work of art that somebody made
before it became a tick tock mean
um
which
is just pure like personal anecdote but
it's interesting so if we're getting
insulated by like the media we consume
are
we also getting insulated by the type of
music we consume like are we less able
to appreciate other types of music
because i'm listening to the same
song in a lot of different renditions
or are we like broadening our musical
consumption because i'm able to access
music from all over the globe at the
click of a button
it's probably a little bit of both
yeah it's like the space of the action
opens up
when when there's so many affordances in
our niche to select from
yet also
quite curated and presented in a certain
way
that just on aggregate probably still
does drive people to have shared action
and so then like it's literally the
platform
playing that role of the
metronome coupling interaction
there that's interesting that you bring
that up um and also
so if we come to this music is the
strive for social bonding and we've just
been in this global pandemic or we still
are
um but for many people we were
on various stages of lockdowns
music live music was not happening
um choir or musical ensemble rehearsals
were not happening
and you saw this drive to continue to do
something like make music together
online and one of these drives was
she shanties became really popular on
tiktok
and
it's not something that people were
doing together at the same time because
we have this delay that's happening
over
audio visual communication like this it
works well when we're taking turns it's
harder for trying to synchronize and
sing together
so tick-tock allowed someone to record a
sea shanty and then the next person adds
their voice to that recording
and they record their song singing the
sea shanty and then the next person does
the same thing and you end up with these
compilation
not compilations but these like
ensemble performances
of
a song that
um
people would sing when they're off on
ships at sea
and they're feeling um they're like
having this social bond with the people
that they're out at sea with the whole
time and now it's our song that we're
singing through the internet as a way
to
feel like we're having some sort of
social bonding and interacting and
engaging with people and you saw that on
tick tock you also saw that with
celebrities trying um
trying to sing when they all gathered
together to sing imagine we can argue
about whether that went well or not
um
or when we saw
basically there was kind of an explosion
of different types of online music
interaction
to try to replace this local
interaction of going to a concert and
seeing someone
on stage around a group of people that
you're interacting with together or
going to perform or rehearse or jam with
your friends
in your garage
and trying to find digital avenues for
the same
social role that music traditionally
plays
very
interesting
like
and how will it
change going forward
some people may
find very uh
immersive sensory experiences to be
powerful for them maybe that's a
scalable approach maybe it's not maybe
that's a good thing maybe it's not um
so one one other part was like
when you were contrasting the musical
study that you presented first with the
basketball you mentioned that that
environment was unscripted or
um in in in contrast to
sheet music or like a spoken dialogue
that was scripted
and then um in one sense it is
unscripted but then
as per the paper on active inference and
scripts
it's more like the strong and the weak
scripts like the basketball
is a scripted environment in the
cultural norm
weak script
sense so
yes it doesn't have the stage directions
but
you know are there not signs
helping identify where people with a
given ticket should sit
and signals and lights and sounds that
also provide a lot of cues that are
going to be totally specific like the
seventh inning stretch in baseball
why stretch then
but then that's part of where
like the embodiment of even watching the
game
and participating in it gets to be why
it's the phenomena of
entertainment
and why it's something that people spend
their life like supporting directly and
indirectly and practicing for
and why this isn't just like a neural
entrainment
binaural beat hack or something like
that
yeah so if i got the same experience
being at a basketball game sitting in
the student section that i got from
sitting on my couch and watching the
basketball game at home
then you would imagine nobody pays to go
to basketball games and we all sit on
our couch and watch them at home right
but we spend lots of money to go to
basketball games or whatever sporting
events
we have student sections
we wear the colors of our sports team so
we're already signaling to people that
you know i'm wearing this outfit so i'm
a byu fan i'm wearing this other outfit
so i'm a
i don't know basketball teams i was
going to name another one i'm that kind
of fan
so that's already signifying a kind of
script where i know oh yeah you're a
friend we're gonna cheer at the same
time
um and then the game has rules and the
game has
good things that happen if my team
scores a point my response is going to
be to fear if
the other team scores a point i'm going
to be upset so there's already um
a relationship where the the game is
driving the behavior in the stands
and then you have the interactions of
the people next to you the people you
can see next to you and in front of you
the people who you can hear
also behind you
and
there are certain cheers that might
be
scripted just like that musical ensemble
so if there's a certain idiosyncratic
chant that i make
um that's associated with this team and
this mascot we all know this chant we've
learned it
maybe it was
written down maybe it's being broadcast
on the
on the big screen
above the game
maybe there's cheerleaders or a band
who's who's leading a certain cheer
and you're engaging it so even though
it's it's
less scripted in a way than this musical
ensemble
in the sense that it's not written on a
piece of paper that every person is
looking at
they're all aware of the social scripts
that are involved in
a basketball game experience and a
basketball game experience with that
team
or with that student section that you're
sitting in
so you're absolutely right that there's
scripts like this and i think any
interaction you get to
there's going to be some kind of script
there's not going to be something that's
pure interaction nobody's interacting
just on vibes you know
um
there's some social script based on
where the people are
based on
what
context they're in whether they know
each other ahead of time whether there's
some external signal
like clothing
um or if you look like me or you don't
look like me
and that's all going to change
the dynamics it might make
certain forms of interactions
occur more easily
um it might make certain kinds of
interactions
dissipate more easily which
interestingly is something that
we're still studying with metronomes
so metronomes don't only move into
synchrony
if you have two interacting metronomes
they might actually cancel each other
out um or they might
exhibit other
like coming in and out of
synchronous dynamics and if we are still
learning how to understand that in that
physical system
um where there's physical properties
that we can change and measure that are
really simple just you know moving back
and forth in a certain period
is that much more complicated when we're
looking at humans who we seem to have
some sort of free will and we can behave
according to some social rules that we
know about or we could behave completely
contrary to those rules
awesome point that the model system like
you brought up helps us confirm just our
statistics like
before the linear model gets brought out
in one setting
try it on the piece of graph paper and
so this is like the graph paper for
thinking about
semantic or
narrative coordination but one wouldn't
want to be in a non-observable territory
with
kind of flying blind that way
um
and also i think the examples with the
game
and the context coordinating behavior to
different ends
uh
it made me think about where there's
fans from
different teams in the same setting
versus like sections that are separated
and then there's the parents at the game
and maybe like the intention is just to
support people in their play
versus like a professional sports and
then there's like people who are there
for pragmatic value they have literal
money other people have like identity
currency on the line
and uh like feeling like one's
city has a good baseball team and all
these very complex things and so it's
kind of just cool
to
have a model that maybe can blanket off
some of that complexity but also just
recognize the real data that you're
getting from these systems which is
sometimes as you pointed out down to a
single microphone which has many
advantages over visual observation or
like um sensor tracking or anything
and that's what we're observing from the
system
and then there's our process of
doing analysis on that signal because
that's actually what the system is
providing these measurements so it kind
of
does tie in active inference and how
we're modeling these
complex settings without
getting lost in how many possible ways
they can be
cool do you have any other like things
you'd like to add or any other points
you want to bring up
um
no
i think this is really great i really
appreciated the discussion you brought
we covered a lot more than just
interacting groups of people
running from brains to music ai's back
again to people it was really fun
cool thank you very much for joining so
see you anytime
awesome sound good see you bye
alright
you